<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the King. A proclamation prohibiting the importation of all wines of the growth of the Canary Islands, and all further trade and commerce with the said islands, and the inhabitants thereof, until His Majesties pleasure shall be further known.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1666</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B20017</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 12264763</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3531</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 21.h.2[36]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.21.f.1[39d]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 1851.c.8[208]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 1851.c.8[209]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R577</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99890774</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99890774</idno>
            <idno type="VID">192514</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B20017)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 192514)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C9:1[36]; C9:3[179]; C18:1[207]; C18:1[208])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the King. A proclamation prohibiting the importation of all wines of the growth of the Canary Islands, and all further trade and commerce with the said islands, and the inhabitants thereof, until His Majesties pleasure shall be further known.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
                  <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>2 sheets (versos blank)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the assigns of John Bill and Christopher Barker, His Majesties printers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>In the Savoy, [i.e. London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1666.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At end of text: Given at our court at Whitehall the twelfth day of November, 1666. In the eighteenth year of our reign.</note>
                  <note>Steele notation: Arms 61  advan- irregular 2) turned Pleasure.</note>
                  <note>Two copies are filmed consecutively at reel C18:1[207]-[208].</note>
                  <note>Copies at reel C18:1[207]-[208] consist of single sheet.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wine and wine making --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Foreign trade regulation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Commerce --  Canary Islands --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:192514:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <p>HONI · SOLT · QVI · MAL · Y · PENSE ·</p>
                  <p>DIEV · ET · MON · DROIT</p>
               </figure> By the King. A PROCLAMATION Prohibiting the Importation of all Wines of the Growth of the <hi>Canary</hi> Iſlands, and all further Trade and Commerce with the ſaid Iſlands, and the Inhabitants thereof, until His Majeſties Pleaſure ſhall be further known.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>CHARLES R.</signed>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas the Trade of the <hi>Canary</hi>-Wines was heretofore carried on with much benefit and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to Our Subjects, by a great Vent and Exportation of the Native Commodities and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures of Our Kingdoms, and the Wines received in Exchange for thoſe Commodities, were uſually, when Imported, ſold at moderate and eaſie Rates, until of late, by reaſon of the irregular and diſorderly Trading of Retailers, and other perſons no ways experienced in that Trade, and of their extraordinary and unſeaſonable reſort unto the ſaid Iſlands; with an unuſual number of Ships, the Prices of thoſe Wines have beén exceédingly enhaunced, and the Commodities and Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of Our Kingdoms debaſed in their Value by the Inhabitants of the ſaid Iſlands, and Our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects enforced to pay for a great part of thoſe Wines with Pieces of Eight, and Bills of Exchange, to the decay of Trade, and the decreaſe of the Treaſure of Our Kingdoms: And whereas the Inhabitants of thoſe Iſlands not contenting themſelves with the Baniſhment of Our Conſul, and the principal Factors out of the Iſland of <hi>Theneriff</hi> laſt year, have lately proceéded further, and do openly Declare, That no <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ship whatſoever ſhall be permitted to Load or Vnload, or any <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchant to live amongſt them; And the Governours of the ſaid Iſlands have publiſhed ſeveral Proclamations to that effect, and executed them with ſuch ſeverity, That all Our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants lately reſiding in thoſe Iſlands, are quite turned off the ſaid Iſlands, and forced to leave their Eſtates behind them, to their utter ruine. We therefore deép<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſenting theſe injuries done to all Our loving Subjects, and reſolving not to ſuffer the Indignities offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Our Self, have thought fit by the advice of Our Council, to Declare, and do hereby Publiſh and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare Our Royal Will and Pleaſure, That no Wines, nor any other Commodities of the Growth, Produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or Manufacture of the <hi>Canary</hi> Iſlands, nor any other Merchandiſe whatſoever from thence, ſhall at any time hereafter be Imported into this Our Kingdom, or into any other of Our Kingdoms and Dominions, until Our Pleaſure ſhall be further known, upon pain of forfeiting all the Wines, Commodities, and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſes ſo Imported, and of incurring the utmoſt Penalty which can be inflicted upon the wilful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temners of this Our Royal Command. And We do hereby Charge and Command all and every of Our loving Subjects, of what degreé and condition ſoever, as well in this Our Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> as in any other of Our Kingdoms or Dominions, That they preſume not to continue any Trade or Traffique with any of the Inhabitants of the ſaid Iſlands, nor to have any further Commerce with them, or ſend any Ship or Ships thither, as they will anſwer the contrary at their perils. And all Merchants and Commanders of Ships now in Port, and Outward bound for the ſaid Iſlands, or any of them, are hereby Commanded not to proceéd in ſuch their Voyage, upon pain of Our utmoſt Diſpleaſure. And We do hereby ſtraitly Charge and Command all Farmers, Collectors, Waiters, and Officers of Our Cuſtoms, and all other Our Officers and Miniſters whatſoever, That they preſume not to ſuffer any Wines of the Growth of the ſaid <hi>Canary</hi> Iſlands, or any other Commodities or Merchandiſe belonging to any of the Inhabitants of the ſaid Iſlands, or coming from thence, for the account of any other perſon or perſons whomſoever, to be Landed at any the Ports of this Our Kingdom, or any other of Our Kingdoms or Dominions, until Our Pleaſure herein ſhall be further known, as they will anſwer the contrary at their perils.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Given at Our Court at Whitehall</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>the Twelfth day of November,</hi> 1666. <hi>In the Eighteenth year of Our Reign.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <closer>God ſave the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>In the <hi>SAVOY,</hi> Printed by the Aſsigns of <hi>John Bill</hi> and <hi>Chriſtopher Barker,</hi> His Majeſties Printers, 1666.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
